Finding Aid for the John H. Cheek Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John H. Cheek Collection
Undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0689
.84 linear_feet
Biographical Notes
John Hancock Cheek, Jr. was the son of John Hancock Cheek, Sr. and Susan E. Glenn Cheek. He was born June 26, 1924. He received his B.A. from Yale University in 1950, and his M.A.(1956) and Ph.D.(1959) from Harvard University. He came to Vanderbilt University in 1958 as a teacher of Russian. Cheek helped establish the Russian language program at Vanderbilt. He was a professor of Russian, Chinese, and Linguistics at Vanderbilt’s Department of Germanic and Slavic Languages. In 1983 he was awarded the title “Emeritus” by the Board of Trust. He died at his home February 20, 2002.
Content and Scope Notes
This collection is composed of one Hollinger box, containing five folders and one book, and one 11x14 Oversize Box. The first box primarily contains notes in the Japanese writing systems of Kana and Kanji. Researchers will also find correspondence from John Cheek to H.P. Scott, regarding Cheek’s English ancestors, and a copy of Vanderbilt’s 1983 Commencement program. Finally a copy of Cheek’s Ph.D. thesis from Harvard University, A Distinctive Feature Phonematic Analysis of Lower Sorbian, is contained within.
The oversize Box contains Cheek’s notes on the First Summer Institute in Chinese Civilization, geography, and Tai Chi Ch’uan as well as a photograph of his son John H. Cheek, III, as a boy. Additionally, researchers will find copies and a cover of magazines detailing the Apollo 11 and Apollo 12 moon landings.
- Notes in Kana and Kanji (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Notes in Kana and Kanji (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes in Kana and Kanji (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from John H. Cheek, Jr. to H.P. Scott, April 6, 1981
- Vanderbilt Commencement Program, May 13, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cheek, John Hancock. A Distinctive Feature Phonematic Analysis of Lower Sorbian: A Synchronic Study. Cambridge: Harvard U. Press, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- First Summer Institute in Chinese Civilization, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Geography Notes (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Tai Chi Ch’uan Notes (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photograph of John Cheek, his son, as a boy, c. late 1950’s. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Apollo 11: Man and the Moon. New York: New York Times. 1969. Print. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Life, Off to the Moon: Special Issue. Chicago: Time. July 4, 1969. Print. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Life, Leaving For The Moon. Chicago: Time. July 25, 1969. Print. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Life, Apollo 12: On the Moon. Chicago: Time. December 12, 1969. Print (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Apollo 11: On the Moon, A Look Special. New York; New York Times. 1969. Print. (Box 2, Folder 9)